{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "The oldest river valley project in India is",
            "optionA": "  Hirakund ",
            "optionB": "  Damodar ",
            "optionC": "  Chambal ",
            "optionD": "  Kosi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOnce known as 'Sorrow of West Bengal' because of its devastating floods, the Damodar river was curtailed (tamed) by building of Multi Purpose River Valley Project,a series of dams and canals. Idea was taken from Tennesses River Valley Project, U.S.A. ",
            "keyString": "126931s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which place is said to be the Manchester of South India?",
            "optionA": "  Coimbatore ",
            "optionB": "  Salem ",
            "optionC": "  Thanjavur ",
            "optionD": "  Madurai ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCoimbatore is 'Manchester of South India'. As it has thousands small, medium, large industries & textile mills. ",
            "keyString": "126963s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In India, the Black Revolution is related to the manufacturing of which product?",
            "optionA": "  Charcoal ",
            "optionB": "  Crude petroleum ",
            "optionC": "  Diamond ",
            "optionD": "  Black gram ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCrude petroleum is originally found in black colour. It is also known as 'Black Gold'. In order to increase theproduction of crude oil, the term \"Black Revolution\" was coined in India.",
            "keyString": "126979s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first month of the 'Saka era' is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Vaishakha ",
            "optionB": "  Phalguna ",
            "optionC": "  Chaitra ",
            "optionD": "  Bhadon ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first month of the 'Saka era' is Chaitra. The national calendar based on the Saka Era, with Chaitra as its first month and a normal year of 365 days was adopted from 22 March 1957 along with the Gregorian calendar for the following official purposes: Gazette of India. ",
            "keyString": "126992s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Integral coach factory is in",
            "optionA": "  Perambur (Chennai) ",
            "optionB": "  Bengaluru ",
            "optionC": "  Varanasi ",
            "optionD": "  Howrah (Kolkata) ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIntegral Coach Factory is located in Perambur, Chennai, Tamil Nadu. It was established in 1952, is owned and operated by the Indian Railways. ",
            "keyString": "127004s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following city has the largest number of registered vehicles?",
            "optionA": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionB": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionC": "  Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  Chennai ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDue to rapid urbanisation the number of registered vehicles in Delhi is the largest. This data is the outcome of Barclays report titled 'Megatrends Accelerating urbanisation in India'.",
            "keyString": "167212s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is Mumbai High located",
            "optionA": "  Continental Shelf of Arabian sea ",
            "optionB": "  Western Coastal Plain ",
            "optionC": "  Western Ghat ",
            "optionD": "  Internal Plains of South ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn an off shore region of the coast of Mumbai. The petroleum reserves are available under sea on the continent shelf of Arabian Sea. ",
            "keyString": "167251s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ganga beyond Farakka when it enters Bangladesh is known as",
            "optionA": "  Padma ",
            "optionB": "  Meghna ",
            "optionC": "  Hugli ",
            "optionD": "  Swarn Ganga ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGanga beyond Farakka when it enters Bangladesh is known as Padma. Once the Padma reaches the centre of Bangladesh, it joins with the Brahmaputra, or Jamuna, as it is known in Bangladesh, where the two join and form the Meghna River. The Farakka Barrage was created by India in 1975 to divert water from the Ganges River to the Bhagirathi-Hoogly river system. ",
            "keyString": "167269s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India's longest tunnel Jawahar tunnel is located in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Jammu and Kashmir ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionD": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJawahar Tunnel in Jammu & Kashmir was named after 1st P.M. Jawahar Lal Nehru. It is also known as Banihal Tunnel as it links Qazigund with Banihal. It lies on NH44. ",
            "keyString": "167282s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which from the following towns is not on the \"Golden Quadrilateral\" being created for the roads-infrastructure of the country?",
            "optionA": "  Ajmer ",
            "optionB": "  Ahmedabad ",
            "optionC": "  Jabalpur ",
            "optionD": "  Gaya ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJabalpur is not on the \"Golden Quadrilateral\" being created for the roads-infrastructure of the country. The Golden Quadrilateral is a highway network connecting many of the major industrial, agricultural and cultural centers of India. A quadrilateral of sorts is formed by connecting Chennai, Kolkata, Delhi and Mumbai, and hence its name\u201d. ",
            "keyString": "167296s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The national highway from Amritsar to Kolkata via Delhi is numbered",
            "optionA": "  1 ",
            "optionB": "  2 ",
            "optionC": "  4 ",
            "optionD": "  8 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational Highway from Amritsar to Calcutta via Delhi is called National highway No. 2. It was called Grand Trunk road and was constructed by Sher Shah. ",
            "keyString": "208831s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With reference to National Highways Development Project (NHDP), consider the following statements:\n1. Belgaum and Nellore lie on the Golden Quadrilateral.\n2. Vadodara and Jhansi lie on the East - West Corridor.\n3. Ambala and Kanpur lie on the North - South Corridor.\nWhich of these statements is/are correct ?",
            "optionA": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  2 and 3 ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  1 only ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWith reference to National Highways Development Project (NHDP), the following statement that is true is Belgaum and Nellore lie on the Golden Quadrilateral. It forms a quadrilateral connecting the four major metro cities of India, viz., Delhi (north), Kolkata (east), Mumbai (west) and Chennai (south). Other cities connected by this network include Ahmedabad, Bengaluru, Balasore, Bhubaneswar, Cuttack,Durgapur, Jaipur, Kanpur, Pune, Surat, Vijayawada, Ajmer, Vizag, Bodhgaya, Varanasi, Agra, Mathura, Dhanbad, Gandhinagar, Udaipur, and Vadodara. ",
            "keyString": "208866s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the longest National Highway in India?",
            "optionA": "  NH4 ",
            "optionB": "  NH44 ",
            "optionC": "  NH10 ",
            "optionD": "  NH5 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNH44 with a length of about 3,745 km is the longest national highway in India. Although NH7 running over 12,369 km is longest \"Single\" national highway in India. NH44 is a merger of different national highways and runs from Srinagar to Kanyakumari. ",
            "keyString": "208888s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one is not located on National Highway-2 (NH-2)?",
            "optionA": "  Aurangabad ",
            "optionB": "  Sasaram ",
            "optionC": "  Mohania ",
            "optionD": "  Patna ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSasaram is not located on National Highway-2 (NH-2). National Highway 19 a National Highway in India that links Ghazipur in Uttar Pradesh with Patna in Bihar. Sasaram is located in NH-19. ",
            "keyString": "208903s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which National Highway connects Chennai and Visakhapatnam ?",
            "optionA": "  NH 4 ",
            "optionB": "  NH 5 ",
            "optionC": "  NH 6 ",
            "optionD": "  NH 8 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNH 5 Chennai and Visakhapatnam.NH -5 is situated in Visakhapatnam, India. ",
            "keyString": "208917s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is Kandla Port located in?",
            "optionA": "  Gulf of Kutch ",
            "optionB": "  Kori Creek ",
            "optionC": "  Gulf of Khambhat ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKandla port is located in Kutch, Gujarat near Gandhidham city on Gulf of Kutch. It was built to compensate the loss of Karachi port to Pakistan. ",
            "keyString": "256751s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Among the following cities, which one is at the highest altitude above mean sea level?",
            "optionA": "  Bangalore ",
            "optionB": "  Delhi ",
            "optionC": "  Jodhpur ",
            "optionD": "  Nagpur ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBangalore is at the highest altitude above mean sea level. Bangalore is the city which is 937 metres above sea level, Delhi is 218 metres sea level, Jodhpur is 230 metres and Nagpur is 247.5 metres above the sea level. ",
            "keyString": "256783s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The last three digits of a PIN code represent ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Zone ",
            "optionB": "  Sub-zone ",
            "optionC": "  Sorting district ",
            "optionD": "  Mailing route ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe last three digits of a PIN code represent sorting district. The first digit of the PIN indicates the zone. The second digit indicates the sub-zone, and the third digit indicates the sorting district within that zone. ",
            "keyString": "256799s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There is always shortage of electricity in India for a long time, because",
            "optionA": "  There is fluctuation in hydro-power generation ",
            "optionB": "  Demand for electricity is increasing while its\ngeneration and distribution has not been\nincreased ",
            "optionC": "  The objective of getting new capacity is not\nachieved ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs the population increases, the demanad for almost all commodities & energy sources increases, same is the case in India, even rapid industrialisation requires power supply. But till date energy produced in terms of electricity is less than what is required to be consumed.",
            "keyString": "256812s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Put the following states in the decreasing order by length of surfaced roads:\n1. Maharashtra\n2. Karnataka\n3. Tamil Nadu\n4. Uttar Pradesh",
            "optionA": "  1, 2, 3, 4 ",
            "optionB": "  4, 1, 3, 2 ",
            "optionC": "  1, 3, 4, 2 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 3, 2, 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following states in the decreasing order by length of surfaced roads are Maharashtra, Tamil Nadu, Uttar Pradesh and Karnataka. ",
            "keyString": "256824s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Golden Quadrilateral Project for the development of National Highways was initiated by",
            "optionA": "  P V Narasimha Rao ",
            "optionB": "  I K Gujral ",
            "optionC": "  Manmohan Singh ",
            "optionD": "   Atal Bihari Vajpayee ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGolden Quadrilateral Project was initiated by former PM Atal Bihari Vajpayee. Its main objective is to connect major industrial areas (regions) of the country to assistsmooth transportation and communication. It connects Delhi, Kolkata, Chennai and Mumbai.",
            "keyString": "372921s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The National Highway-1D connects Leh to Kashmir Valley through the ________ pass.",
            "optionA": "  Khyber ",
            "optionB": "  Zoji la ",
            "optionC": "  Nathula ",
            "optionD": "  Karakoram ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tZoji La is located in western section of Himalayan Mountain ranges and lies on National Highway-1D between Leh and Kashmir valley. ",
            "keyString": "373562s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If a truck has to carry goods from Delhi to Bhopal via Gwalior, by National Highways (NH) following the shortest route, which one of the following groups of National Highways it has to go by ?",
            "optionA": "  NH 2, NH 11, NH 12 ",
            "optionB": "  NH 2, NH 3, NH 12 ",
            "optionC": "  NH 8, NH 3, NH 11 ",
            "optionD": "  NH 2, NH 25, NH 11 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIf a truck has to carry goods from Delhi to Bhopal via Gwalior, by National Highways (NH) following the shortest route, it has to go by NH 2, NH 3 and NH 12. ",
            "keyString": "375420s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Karakoram Highway connects which of the following pairs of countries?",
            "optionA": "  India-Nepal ",
            "optionB": "  India-China ",
            "optionC": "  India-Pakistan ",
            "optionD": "  China-Pakistan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Karakoram Highway connects China-Pakistan. The Karakorum Highway connects China and Pakistan across the Karakoram mountain range, through the Khunjerab Pass, at an elevation of 4,693 metres (15,397 ft) above the sea level. The road is one of the scariest and hair raising jeep trip in the world.",
            "keyString": "376601s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The National Highway - 1 connects Delhi to",
            "optionA": "  Chennai ",
            "optionB": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionC": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionD": "  Amritsar ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe National Highway - 1 connects Delhi to Amritsar. The strip from Amritsar to Jalandhar is four-lane and from Jalandhar to Delhi. ",
            "keyString": "378045s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India is divided into how many pin code zones?",
            "optionA": "  Six ",
            "optionB": "  Seven ",
            "optionC": "  Eight ",
            "optionD": "  Ten ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are 9 PIN regions in the country. The first 8 are geographical regions and the digit 9 is reserved for the Army Postal Service. ",
            "keyString": "483649s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The National highways system is the responsibility of",
            "optionA": "  State Governments ",
            "optionB": "  Central Government ",
            "optionC": "  A special Roads Authority ",
            "optionD": "  State and Central Government ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe National highways system is the responsibility of Central Government. Under the National Highways Act, 1956, National Highways became the responsibility of the central government. ",
            "keyString": "486557s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which National Highway connects Delhi and Kolkata via Varanasi",
            "optionA": "  NH4 ",
            "optionB": "  NH10 ",
            "optionC": "  NH2 ",
            "optionD": "  NH6 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational Highway (NH2) connects 6 states of North India i.e. Delhi, Haryana, U.P. Bihar, Jharkhand & West Bengal constituting a portion of Grand Trunk Road. ",
            "keyString": "486606s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following National Highways passes through Maharashtra, Chhattisgarh and Orissa?",
            "optionA": "  NH 4 ",
            "optionB": "  NH 5 ",
            "optionC": "  NH 6 ",
            "optionD": "  NH 7 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNH 6 passes through Maharashtra, Chhattisgarh and Orissa. NH6 ran through Gujarat, Maharashtra, Chhattisgarh, Odisha, Jharkhand and West Bengal state in India. ",
            "keyString": "486976s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following National Highways of India is the longest?",
            "optionA": "  NH 1 ",
            "optionB": "  NH 2 ",
            "optionC": "  NH 3 ",
            "optionD": "  NH 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNH 2 of India is the longest. National Highway 2 is a national highway in India that runs from Dibrugarh in Assam to Tuipang in Mizoram. Its length is 1,214 km (754 mi). ",
            "keyString": "487338s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Railway zones and their Headquarters is not correct?",
            "optionA": "  North-Eastern-Gorakhpur ",
            "optionB": "  South-Central-Hyderabad ",
            "optionC": "  Eastern-Kolkata ",
            "optionD": "  Western-Mumbai ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSouth-Central-Hyderabad is not correct. Secunderabad Division was split into two Divisions viz. Secunderabad and Hyderabad on 17-Feb-1978. Following re-organisation of zones and Divisions with effect from 01-04-2003, two new Divisions viz., Guntur and Nanded were operationalised duly transferring Hubli Division to newly formed South Western Railway. ",
            "keyString": "566025s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which one of the following places is the headquarters of the North-Eastern Railway located?",
            "optionA": "  Guwahati ",
            "optionB": "  Gorakhpur ",
            "optionC": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionD": "  Bhubaneswar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Gorakhpur the headquarters of the North-Eastern Railway located. The North Eastern Railway is one of the 18 railway zones in India. It is headquartered at Gorakhpur and comprises 3 divisions. ",
            "keyString": "566381s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Wheels and axles for railways are produced",
            "optionA": "  At Bengaluru ",
            "optionB": "  At Chennai ",
            "optionC": "  At Varanasi ",
            "optionD": "  Nowhere in India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRail Wheel Factory (Formerly known as Wheel and Axle Plant) is situated inBangalore, Karnataka, India. It is a state-of-the-art plant, meeting bulk of the requirement of wheels, axles and wheel sets for the Indian Railways. The spare capacity available is profitably utilised to meet the domestic demands for non-railway customers and exports. ",
            "keyString": "569492s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main drawback of the railway network in India is",
            "optionA": "  Lack of rolling stock ",
            "optionB": "  Existence of single track in many areas ",
            "optionC": "  Lack of coal ",
            "optionD": "  The presence of three types of gauges ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main drawback of the railway network in India is the presence of three types of gauges. Types of rail gauges used in Indian railways are Broad gauge (B.G.) 1676 mm, Meter gauge (M.G.) 1000mm and Narrow gauge(N.G.) 762mm. ",
            "keyString": "570872s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Konkan Railway connects",
            "optionA": "  Goa - Mangalore ",
            "optionB": "  Roha - Mangalore ",
            "optionC": "  Kanyakumari - Mangalore ",
            "optionD": "  Kanyakumari - Mumbai ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRoha lies in Maharashtra & Mangalore lies in Karnataka. These two are end points of Konkan Railway. Konkan Railway passes through Maharashtra, Goa & Karnataka. ",
            "keyString": "572059s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Damodar Valley Project concerns two states",
            "optionA": "  Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  West Bengal and Jharkhand ",
            "optionC": "  Maharashtra and Karnataka ",
            "optionD": "  Haryana and Punjab ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Damodar Valley Project concerns two states : West Bengal and Jharkhand. ",
            "keyString": "644227s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which state irrigation is done by Rihand Dam project?",
            "optionA": "  Gujarat and Maharashtra ",
            "optionB": "  Orissa and West Bengal ",
            "optionC": "   Uttar Pradesh and Bihar ",
            "optionD": "   Uttar Pradesh and Bihar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRihand Dam also called as Govind Ballabh Pant Sagar is built across river Rihand. It is located in Sonbhadra district of Uttar Pradesh. Its reservoir lies on boundary between Uttar Pradesh & Madhya Pradesh. Riharid is the tributary of Son river. ",
            "keyString": "645103s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nagarjuna Sagar Dam is constructed on which river",
            "optionA": "  Kaveri ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna ",
            "optionC": "  Godavari ",
            "optionD": "  Indus ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNagarjuna Sagar Dam is built on Krishna river forming boundary between Nalgonda of Telangana & Guntur of Andhra pradesh. It is a multi purpose project. ",
            "keyString": "645575s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The world's longest masonry dam is",
            "optionA": "  Hirakud ",
            "optionB": "  Bhakra Nangal ",
            "optionC": "  Nagarjuna Sagar ",
            "optionD": "  Aswan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNagarjuna Sagar, which is situated across the Krishna River on the border between Guntur district, Andra Pradesh, and Nalgonda district, Telangana, is the world's largest masonry dam. This dam, with a gross storage capacity of 11.472 billion cubic meters, was built between 1955 and 1967. From its lowest base, it is also 590 feet (180 m ) tall and 0.99 miles long with 26 flood gates that are 42 feet (13 m) wide and 45 feet (14 m ) tall. ",
            "keyString": "646212s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nagarjunasagar Dam was built on",
            "optionA": "  Mahanadi river ",
            "optionB": "  Damodar river ",
            "optionC": "  Krishna river ",
            "optionD": "  Cauvery river ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNagarjunasagar Dam was built on Krishna river. The construction commenced in 1955 and took 12 years for its completion. This place is at a distance of about 160 Kms from Hyderabad. ",
            "keyString": "647501s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following newly manufacturing unit is going to be established by Indian railway?",
            "optionA": "  Rail Coach Factory, Kapurthala ",
            "optionB": "  Wheel Factory, Chapra ",
            "optionC": "   Wheel and Axle Plant, Durgapur ",
            "optionD": "  Rail Wheel Factory, Bengaluru ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRail Wheel Factory was setup in the year 2008 in Saran district of Bihar. It was inaugrated by the thenRailway Minister Sh. Lalu Prasad Yadav. It is first indigenously developed sophisticated factory of its type in India. It is developedby Larsen & Tourbo. ",
            "keyString": "727285s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which city is the headquarters of two Railway zones in India?",
            "optionA": "  Hugli ",
            "optionB": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionC": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionD": "  Jabalpur ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are overall 18 zones & 69 divisions of Indian Railways. Of these Mumbai is the headquarter of two zones. They are Central Railway & Western Railway. ",
            "keyString": "727343s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The width or the broad gauge track in Indian railway is",
            "optionA": "  1.676 m ",
            "optionB": "  1.114 m ",
            "optionC": "  1.98 m ",
            "optionD": "  2.55 m ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe width or the broad gauge track in Indian railway is 1676 mm (1.676 m). ",
            "keyString": "727740s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The longest railway platform in India",
            "optionA": "  Amritsar ",
            "optionB": "  Gorakhpur ",
            "optionC": "  Kathgodam ",
            "optionD": "  Kanpur ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGorakhpur Junction's railway platform is the longest railway platform in India. Length of this platform is 1.3 km. Before this Khadagpur was the longest platform with length of about 1074m. ",
            "keyString": "728089s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following pairs is not correctly matched? Railway : Zone Headquarters",
            "optionA": "  North Eastern Railway : Gorakhpur ",
            "optionB": "  South Eastern Railway : Bhubhaneswar ",
            "optionC": "  Eastern Railway : Kolkata ",
            "optionD": "  South East Central Railway : Bilaspur ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBhubaneswar Railway Station (BBS) serves Bhubaneswar, the capital of the Indian state of Odisha and it is the headquarters of the East Coast Railway zone of the Indian Railways. ",
            "keyString": "728434s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the largest tiger reserve in India?",
            "optionA": "  Nagarjuna ",
            "optionB": "  Manas ",
            "optionC": "  Pench ",
            "optionD": "  Corbett ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCorbett is the largest tiger reserve in India. Jim Corbett, this National Park was set up in 1936. It is often considered as India\u2019s first National Park and has an interesting variety of fauna and flora.It is located in the Patli Dun valley in the state of Uttar Pradesh and covers an enormous core area of 500 sq km. ",
            "keyString": "815381s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is located in the Bastar region?",
            "optionA": "  Bandhavgarh National Park ",
            "optionB": "  Dandeli Sanctuary ",
            "optionC": "  Rajaji National Park ",
            "optionD": "  Indravati National Park ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndravati National Park is located in the Bastar region. Indravati National Park is a national park located in Bijapur district of Chhattisgarh state of India. It derives its name from the nearby Indravati River.",
            "keyString": "815433s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which two of the followig are connected by the North South Corridor?",
            "optionA": "  Srinagar and Kanyakumari ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai and Chennai ",
            "optionC": "   Amritsar and Kolkata ",
            "optionD": "  Hyderabad and Bhopal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe North South Corridor & East West Corridor are being developed to enhance the transportation &, communication throuhout the country. The North South Corridor runs from Srinagar to Kanyakumari. ",
            "keyString": "817094s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is the most possible solution for planning improvement of a metropolitan city in India?",
            "optionA": "  Constructing high rise building and sky scrapers ",
            "optionB": "  Dispersing the factories & industries to the neighbouring but independent location. ",
            "optionC": "  Building up suburbs and satellite towns around the main city ",
            "optionD": "  Preventing immigration of people into the metropolitan city ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDispersing the factories & industries to the neighbouring but independent location is the most possible solution for planning improvement of a metropolitan city in India. ",
            "keyString": "817911s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following towns is not on the \"Golden Quadrilateral\" being created for the roads infrastructure of the country ?",
            "optionA": "  Chennai ",
            "optionB": "  Hyderabad ",
            "optionC": "  Vishakhapatnam ",
            "optionD": "  Bhubhaneshwar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHyderabad is not on the \"Golden Quadrilateral\" being created for the roads infrastructure of the country. The Golden Quadrilateral is a highway network connecting many of the major industrial, agricultural and cultural centers of India. A quadrilateral of sorts is formed by connecting Chennai, Kolkata, Delhi and Mumbai, and hence its name\u201d. ",
            "keyString": "825313s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The commodity which accounts for the maximum volume of goods transported by the railways in India is",
            "optionA": "  Iron and steel ",
            "optionB": "  Coal ",
            "optionC": "  Mineral oil ",
            "optionD": "  Metallic ores (other than iron ore) ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe commodity which accounts for the maximum volume of goods transported by the railways in India is Coal. The Railways has achieved its highest-ever freight loading in fiscal 2018, supported largely by the additional transport of commodities such as coal, cement and containers. Transporting goods by train is cheaper. ",
            "keyString": "910307s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following sea Port is nearest to Rourkela Steel Plant?",
            "optionA": "  Haldia ",
            "optionB": "  Vishakhapattanam ",
            "optionC": "  Kandla ",
            "optionD": "  Paradip ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRourkela Steel Plant is located in Rourkela, Odisha. It is closer to Paradip port when compared with other ports. As iron is heavy and weighty, it is exported from nearby Pradip port,Odisha.",
            "keyString": "910361s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which ports are located on the Eastern coast of India?",
            "optionA": "  Kandla and Haldia ",
            "optionB": "  Haldia and Kochin ",
            "optionC": "  Paradip and Kandla ",
            "optionD": "  Paradip and Haldia ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKandla & Kochi are located on the west coast of India. Kandla in Gujarat, Kochi in Kerala whereas Paradip is in Odisha & Haldia is in West Bengal on Eastern Coast. ",
            "keyString": "910736s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The First port developed after independence was",
            "optionA": "  New Mangalore ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionC": "  Nhava Sheva ",
            "optionD": "  Kandla ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKandla was developed as an off spring port. As due to partition India lost important Karachi port to Pakistanso Mumbai port was over burdened with excess work. This effect was neutralised by diverting trade to Kandla port which situate in Kutch district Gujarat. ",
            "keyString": "910897s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the correct sequence of hill stations according to height above mean sea level in descending order?",
            "optionA": "  Kodaikanal, Darjeeling, Shimla and Mahabaleshwar ",
            "optionB": "  Shimla, Kodaikanal, Darjeeling and Mahabaleshwar ",
            "optionC": "  Kodaikanal, Shimla, Mahabaleshwar and Darjeeling ",
            "optionD": "  Mahabaleshwar, Shimla, Darjeeling and Kodaikanal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe correct sequence of hill stations according to height above mean sea level in descending order are Shimla-2,276 m, Kodaikanal-2,133 m, Darjeeling-2,042 m and Mahabaleshwar-1,353 m. ",
            "keyString": "911923s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the destination of the slurry brought by pipeline from Kudremukh?",
            "optionA": "  Koyali ",
            "optionB": "  Jagdishpur ",
            "optionC": "  Mangalore ",
            "optionD": "  Udaipur ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIron ore is mined from the hills of Kudremukh in Chikmagaluru District of Karnataka in Western Ghats. From here it is transported to the port of Mangalore in the formslurry through pipeline for exports. ",
            "keyString": "995909s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 'Grand Trunk Road' connects ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Kolkata and Mumbai ",
            "optionB": "  Delhi and Chennai ",
            "optionC": "  Kolkata and Amritsar ",
            "optionD": "  Tirupati and Ludhiana ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 'Grand Trunk Road' connects Kolkata and Amritsar. G.T road is a part of India's Golden Quadrilateral project (4\u20136 lane highway ) Connecting Amritsar via Delhi, Agra, Kanpur, Allahabad, Varanasi, Dhanbad, Asansol with Kolkata. ",
            "keyString": "995965s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Buckingham Canal, which has been declared a National Waterway of India recently, is a canal running from",
            "optionA": "  Punjab to Haryana ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai to Goa ",
            "optionC": "  Vijayawada to Villupuram ",
            "optionD": "  Cochin to Kozhikode ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Buckingham Canal, which has been declared a National Waterway of India recently, is a canal running from Vijayawada to Villupuram. The Buckingham Canal is a 420 km long salt water navigation canal, running parallel to the Coromandel Coast of South India from the vijayawada in Andhra Pradesh to Villupuram District in Tamil Nadu declared national waterway of India. ",
            "keyString": "996139s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arrange these places in decreasing order of their atmospheric pressure on their ground surface:\n1. Shimla\n2. Gangtok\n3. Mumbai\n4. Delhi",
            "optionA": "  3, 4, 1, 2 ",
            "optionB": "  4, 3, 2, 1 ",
            "optionC": "  3, 1, 4, 2 ",
            "optionD": "  2, 4, 1, 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe places in decreasing order of their atmospheric pressure on their ground surface are Delhi, Mumbai, Gangtok and Shimla. ",
            "keyString": "996529s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following cities in India is not located in Golden Quadrilateral Road Network?",
            "optionA": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionC": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionD": "   Chandigarh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChandigarh in India is not located in Golden Quadrilateral Road Network. Golden Quadrilateral Road network connects 4 major metropolis cities of India i.e, Delhi, Kolkata, Chennai & Mumbai to enhance communication & transportation. ",
            "keyString": "996968s52m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is an important port of Eastern coast of India?",
            "optionA": "  Kandla ",
            "optionB": "  Visakhapatnam ",
            "optionC": "  Karaikal ",
            "optionD": "  Puducherry ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVishakkapatnam (Vizag) is used for bulk transportation of iron to East Asian countries such as Japan & South Korea. ",
            "keyString": "113205s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "HBJ pipeline transports",
            "optionA": "  Crude Oil ",
            "optionB": "  Natural Gas ",
            "optionC": "  Petroleum ",
            "optionD": "  Iron Ore in slurry form ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHBJ pipeline also known as HVJ pipeline was started in 1986 by GAIL (India) limited to transport gas to fertilizer plants in U.P.HBJ stands for Hazira - Vijaipur - Jagdishpur. Vijaypur is also termed as Bijeypur. ",
            "keyString": "113466s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is not the port town of Gujarat ?",
            "optionA": "  Jamnagar ",
            "optionB": "  Okha ",
            "optionC": "  Porbandar ",
            "optionD": "  Verval ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJamnagar is not the port town of Gujarat. Bedi Port lies around 8 km from Jamnagar Railway Station on the south-eastern coast of Gulf of Kutch. It is an all-weather trading hub in the Arabian Sea and one of the most prominent ones in Jamnagar. ",
            "keyString": "113500s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is Jawaharlal Nehru Port?",
            "optionA": "  Paradip ",
            "optionB": "  Kochin ",
            "optionC": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionD": "  Kolkata ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJawahar Lal Nehru port is also knows as Nhava Sheva port. It is located to the east of Mumbai , Maharashtra on Arbian Sea.",
            "keyString": "113610s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kolkata Port is an example of which type of port?",
            "optionA": "  Naval ",
            "optionB": "  Oil ",
            "optionC": "  Riverine ",
            "optionD": "  Natural ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRiverin ports are the one's which are further inside from the sea coasts along the stream of a river. Such as Kolkata port is riverine port on river Hooghly. ",
            "keyString": "113711s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the old and over 2 km-long 'Pamban Railway Bridge', which attracts tourists from all over the country?",
            "optionA": "  Nilgiris ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna delta ",
            "optionC": "  Palk straits ",
            "optionD": "  Malabar coast ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPalk straits is the old and over 2 km-long 'Pamban Railway Bridge', which attracts tourists from all over the country. ",
            "keyString": "161753s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Railways are more in North Indian plains because",
            "optionA": "  The area is more productive ",
            "optionB": "  It is densely populated ",
            "optionC": "  The region offers least physical resistance ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRailways are more in North Indian plains because The area is more productive, It is densely populated and The region offers least physical resistance. ",
            "keyString": "161805s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The position of Indian Railways network in the world is",
            "optionA": "  Second ",
            "optionB": "  Third ",
            "optionC": "  Fourth ",
            "optionD": "  Fifth ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Railways is today the largest rail network in Asia and the world's second largest network operated under a single management. It has 115,000 km of track length. ",
            "keyString": "161948s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the major centre of production of railway wagons?",
            "optionA": "  Asansol ",
            "optionB": "  Chittaranjan ",
            "optionC": "  Jamshedpur ",
            "optionD": "  Perambur ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAsansol is the major centre of production of railway wagons. Chittaranjan Locomotive Works is a state-owned electric locomotive manufacturer based in India. It is located at Chittaranjan in Asansol. It is one of the largest locomotive manufacturers in the world. Chittaranjan Locomotive Works has supplied many types of locomotives. ",
            "keyString": "162069s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following railway zones has the maximum route length in kilometres?",
            "optionA": "  Northern ",
            "optionB": "  Southern ",
            "optionC": "  Central ",
            "optionD": "  Western ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNorthern railway zones has the maximum route length in kilometres. Northern Railways is one of nine old zones of Indian Railways and also the biggest in terms of network having 6807 kilometre route. ",
            "keyString": "162178s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Air travel has become very important for the north eastern part of India mainly because _________",
            "optionA": "  The region is mountainous ",
            "optionB": "  Population density is low ",
            "optionC": "  Surface transport routes have to go around Bangladesh ",
            "optionD": "  Air transport is cheaper ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAir travel has become very important for the north eastern part of India mainly because surface transport routes have to go around Bangladesh. ",
            "keyString": "282718s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was not one of the consequences of the policy of exporting raw materials and food grains from India to Britain?",
            "optionA": "  It raised the prices of raw materials ",
            "optionB": "  It brought enormous profits to unscrupulous businessman ",
            "optionC": "  It led to agricultural shortage and famines ",
            "optionD": "  It denuded the country of her agricultural surplus ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe consequences of the policy of exporting raw materials and food grains from India to Britain were that it raised the prices of raw materials, it brought enormous profits to unscrupulous businessman and It denuded the country of her agricultural surplus. ",
            "keyString": "282759s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following is a correct sequence of the Indian ports from north to south?",
            "optionA": "  Haldia - Kandla - Paradeep - Kochi ",
            "optionB": "  Kandla - Haldia - Paradeep - Kochi ",
            "optionC": "  Kandla - Haldia - Kochi - Paradeep ",
            "optionD": "  Kochi - Kandla - Haldia - Paradeep ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe correct sequence of the Indian ports from north to south is Kandla - Haldia - Paradeep - Kochi. ",
            "keyString": "282860s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is the major item of export from Paradeep Port ?",
            "optionA": "  Rice ",
            "optionB": "  Tea ",
            "optionC": "  Fish ",
            "optionD": "  Iron Ore ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIron Ore is the major item of export from Paradeep Port. ",
            "keyString": "282976s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the port is not a Natural Port?",
            "optionA": "  Chennai ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionC": "  Cochin ",
            "optionD": "  Paradip ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChennai Port is an artificial deep seaport as it has been prepared artificially by cutting crust of continental shelf lying under shallow sea zone. Natural deep sea ports are found on Western Ghats of India due to thin coast line where as due to wide continental shelf on easter side, ports here are artificially built. ",
            "keyString": "283067s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian Wild Ass (Ghor-Khur) is found in ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Sunderbans ",
            "optionB": "  Assam forests ",
            "optionC": "  The Rann of Kachch ",
            "optionD": "  Cauvery delta ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian Wild Ass (Ghor-Khur) is found in The Rann of Kachch. The Indian Wild Ass (Equus hemionus khur), also called Ghor Khar or Ghud Khur is found predominantly in the Little Rann of Kutch and its surrounding areas in Gujarat. It is also found in southern Pakistan, Afghanistan, and south-eastern Iran. Saline deserts (Rann), arid grasslands and shrub lands are its preferred environment. ",
            "keyString": "386934s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There is a project in India which is similar to T.V.A. (Tenacy Valley Authority) of USA,it is",
            "optionA": "  Ramganga Multi Purpose Project ",
            "optionB": "  Idukki Project ",
            "optionC": "  Damodar Valley Project ",
            "optionD": "  Mahanadi Delta Project ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDamodar Valley Project is the Multipurpose River Valley Project which is based on Tennessee (River) Valley Authority of U.S.A. This project serves multi dimensional aspects such as hydroelectricty, irrigation, flood control, recreational reservoir etc. ",
            "keyString": "386969s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nal Sarovar Bird Sanctuary is located in ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Maharashtra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNal Sarovar Bird Sanctuary is located in Gujarat. Nalsarovar-Ahmedabad distance is about 60 km located near Sanand Village, in Gujarat. Mainly inhabited by migratory birds as their wintering ground, Nalsarovar is the largest wetland bird sanctuary in Gujarat, and one of the largest in India. ",
            "keyString": "386987s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The highest dam from the following in India is",
            "optionA": "  Maithan ",
            "optionB": "  Bhakra ",
            "optionC": "  Hirakud ",
            "optionD": "  Machkund ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe highest dam from the following in India is Bhakra. ",
            "keyString": "387003s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which dam in India has the distinction of being the longest main stream dam in the world?",
            "optionA": "  Bhakra Nangal Dam ",
            "optionB": "  Rihand Dam ",
            "optionC": "  Tehri Dam ",
            "optionD": "  Kosi Project ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTehri Dam has the distinction of being the longest main stream dam in the world. ",
            "keyString": "387300s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which states are related with the dispute of \"Mullaperiyar dam\"",
            "optionA": "  Karnataka and Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionB": "  Tamil Nadu and Kerala ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala and Karnataka ",
            "optionD": "  Andhra Pradesh and Kamataka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMullaperiyar Dam is also called Mullaiperiyar Dam. It lies on Periyarriver in Idukki district, Kerala. Periyar National Park in Thekkady is located around dam'sreservoir. The location of dam is in Kerala but it is operated & maintained by Tamil Nadu. ",
            "keyString": "458488s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Rail Bandhu\" is",
            "optionA": "  Website of every rail division ",
            "optionB": "  Medical officer in every train to fight in any\nmedical emergency ",
            "optionC": "  Security guard in all air conditioned coaches\nof rajdhani/ shatabadi and duranto trains ",
            "optionD": "  A magazine available of Indian rail available\nin all Rajdhani/ Shatabadi/ AC Duranto Trains ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t'Rail Bandhu' is a monthly magazine from railway. Its target audience is passengers who travel by Rajdhani Express, Shatabdi express & Duranto Express. ",
            "keyString": "458523s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Railway passenger coaches are manufactured at",
            "optionA": "  Varanasi ",
            "optionB": "  Chittaranjan ",
            "optionC": "  Perambur ",
            "optionD": "  Kolkata ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRailway passenger coaches are manufactured at Perambur. The Integral Coach Factory at Perambur has become a leading rail coach manufacturing factory in the world. Chittaranjan Loco Works now produce diesel engines. ",
            "keyString": "458542s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the headquarters of South-Central Railway located?",
            "optionA": "  Itarsi ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionC": "  Secunderabad ",
            "optionD": "  Vijayawada ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t The headquarters of South-Central Railway is located at Secunderabad. Secunderabad Railway Division is one of the six divisions of South Central Railway zone (SCR) of the Indian Railways. It is one of the top five divisions of Indian Railways and its divisional and zonal headquarters are at Secunderabad. ",
            "keyString": "458559s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following States is least developed in rail routes?",
            "optionA": "  Chhattisgarh ",
            "optionB": "  Jharkhand ",
            "optionC": "  Manipur ",
            "optionD": "  Uttaranchal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tManipur state is least developed in rail routes. Manipur has one railway station, Jiribam. ",
            "keyString": "458574s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "National Waterway-I is on which water system?",
            "optionA": "  West Coast Canal ",
            "optionB": "  River Brahamputra ",
            "optionC": "  Ganga, Bhagirathi, Hoogli river ",
            "optionD": "  Sundarbans Waterways ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational waterway-l is a national waterway between Allahabad and Haldia. It has been developed on Ganga,Bhagirathi,Hooghly river system. It became operative in 1986. ",
            "keyString": "533207s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is the correct sequence of the given tiger reserves of India from north to south?",
            "optionA": "  Dudwa - Kanha - Indravati - Bandipur ",
            "optionB": "  Kanha - Bandipur - Dudwa - Indravati ",
            "optionC": "  Indravati - Kanha - Dudwa - Bandipur ",
            "optionD": "  Dudwa - Kanha - Bandipur - Indravati ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe correct sequence of the given tiger reserves of India from north of south is Dudwa - Kanha - Indravati - Bandipur. ",
            "keyString": "533248s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India provides ideal conditions for air travel because",
            "optionA": "  It is a vast country ",
            "optionB": "  It has a huge population ",
            "optionC": "  Its climatic conditions are favourable ",
            "optionD": "  It has extensive mountain tracks ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia provides ideal conditions for air travel because its climatic conditions are favourable. Air density in turn depends mostly on air temperature and elevation; higher temperatures and higher elevations both reduce density. The lower the air density, the faster an airplane must travel to produce enough lift to take off. ",
            "keyString": "533269s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where are the coaches of trains manufactured in India?",
            "optionA": "  Jamshedpur and Perambur ",
            "optionB": "  Kapurthala and Perambur ",
            "optionC": "  Hyderabad and Perambur ",
            "optionD": "  Varanasi and Perambur ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKapurthala in Punjab has Rail Coach Factory located on Jalandhar - Firozpurline. Perambur is a suburban zone in Chennai, Tamil Nadu has Integral Coach Factory.",
            "keyString": "533287s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Asia's first underground Hydel Project is located in which of the following States in India?",
            "optionA": "  Jammu & Kashmir ",
            "optionB": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNathpa Jhakri Dam on river Sutlej is the megal underground dam in Himachal Pradesh with 27.4 km long tunnel. It produces 1500 MW hydro-electricity. ",
            "keyString": "533305s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following railway zones:\n1. North-Eastern Railway\n2. Central Railway\n3. North-Western Railway\n4. South-Eastern Railway\nWhich one of the following is the correct order of locations of the headquarters of the above railway zones from west to east ?",
            "optionA": "  1-2-3-4 ",
            "optionB": "  2-3-1-4 ",
            "optionC": "  3-2-4-1 ",
            "optionD": "  3-4-2-1 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe correct order of locations of the headquarters of the above railway zones from west to east are Central Railway, North-Western Railway, North-Eastern Railway and South-Eastern Railway. ",
            "keyString": "584531s53m26h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}